William Mansfield Clark Papers 1903-1964 Mss.B.C547
American Philosophical Society
- Series III. Research notes, 1907-1962; 3 boxes, 1.25 lin. feet
  - Notebooks #2, [ca. 1953- ] (Box 11)
    "Miscellaneous Experiments, Oct. 1953"
    "Preparations"
  - Notes: "NRC, 1941" and "Corwin's Course, 1952", 1941-1942, 1952-1953 (Box 11)
  - Personal Accounts, 1907-1911 (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1941 November - 1942 December (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1942 December - 1943 February (Box 12)
  - Engagement Notes, 1942, n.d. (Box 12)
    9 3" X 5" cards
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1943 March - 1943 June (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1943 June - 1943 September (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1943 September - 1943 November (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1943 November - 1944 January (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1944 January - 1944 March (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1944 April - 1944 August (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1944 July - 1944 November (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1944 November - 1945 February (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1945 February - 1945 June (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1945 July - 1946 April (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1946 February - 1946 March (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1946 July - 1946 October (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1946 October - 1946 November (Box 12)
  - Notebook; Engagement Book, 1947 April - 1947 June (Box 12)
  - Memorandum Book (Box 12)
  - Notes, n.d. (Box 12)
  - [Notes From Journal Articles], n.d. (Box 12)
    Card file; indexed by journal title
- Series IV. Works by Clark, 1917-1963; 3 boxes, 1.25 lin. feet
  Typescripts and handwritten manuscripts, lectures, reviews of work published by others, and notes, both for lectures as well as for the revision of his Oxidation-Reduction Potentials of Organic Systems. Included are drafts of memorial articles for Barnett Cohen and Leonor Michaelis; Clark's Cutter Lectures delivered at Harvard University in 1930, his 1950 Remsen Memorial Lecture, and the talk he gave at the William H. Nichols Medal award banquet; a few manuscripts regarding the history of the antimalarial drug program; and a manuscript for an article in the Annual Review of Biochemistry entitled, "Notes on a Half-Century of Research, Teaching, and Administration." Also of interest is a manuscript and reprint of "A Critique of Certain Parts of the 1961 Report of the Commission on Enzymes," and an annotated reprint of Clark's address to the 28 December 1933 annual meeting of the Society of American Bacteriologists entitled, "Evolution Toward a Mature Scientific Literature."
  - [Acid-Base Equilibria] -- Lecture notes, n.d (Box 13)
  - "Acid-Base Indicators" -- Manuscript, [1943] (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. I, Simmons, James S.
  - "Address Delivered Before the Washington Chemical Society" -- Lecture notes, 14 October 1920 (Box 13)
  - [Bacterial Metabolism and Hydrogen Ion Concentration]: "[An] Abstract to [the] Am[erican] Soc[iety] of Bact[eriologists]", December 1917 (Box 13)
  - Chemical Anatomy, Physiology and Pathology of Extracellular Fluid. A Lecture Syllabus, by J. L. Gamble -- Review, [1941] (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. I, [Gamble], J. L.
  - "Barnett Cohen, 1891-1952: An Appreciation" -- Manuscript (Box 13)
  - "Barnett Cohen, 1891-1952: Remarks at a Memorial Meeting of Relatives and Friends, October 24th, 1952" -- Manuscript (Box 13)
  - "Color Chart of Indicators" -- Reprint, 1928 (Box 13)
  - "A Critique of Certain Parts of the 1961 Report of the Commission on Enzymes" -- Manuscript and reprint (Box 13)
    - Folder 1, [1963] (Box 13)
    - Folder 2, 1963 (Box 13)
  - "A Critique of Certain Statements in the 1961 Report of the Commission on Enzymes" -- Manuscript, [1963]; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - "The Cutter Lectures on Preventive Medicine: Harvard, First Lecture, April 1, 1930" -- Manuscript (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. II, Harvard University. Cutter Lecture on Preventive Medicine
  - "The Cutter Lectures on Preventive Medicine: Harvard, Second Lecture, April 2, 1930" -- Manuscript (Box 13)
  - "Discussion of [Philip A.] Shaffer's Paper" -- Manuscript, 1933 (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. I, The Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology
  - "Elaboration of Theoretical Detail..." -- Manuscript, 1928 (Box 13)
    humorous
  - Electrometric pH Determinations. Theory and Practice, by Roger G. Bates -- Review, [1954] (Box 13)
  - "Evolution Toward a Mature Scientific Literature" -- Annotated reprint, 1934 (Box 13)
    Presidential address to 1933 annual meet. of Soc. Amer. Bact.
    -see also Ser. I, "Evolution Toward a Mature..."
  - "History" -- Manuscript, n.d. (Box 13)
    Antimalar. drug prog.
  - Hydrogen Ion Concentration: New Concepts in a Systematic Treatment, by John E. Ricci -- Review, n.d. (Box 13)
  - "Hydrogen Ion Determinations," in Simmons and Gentzkow, Medical and Public Health Laboratory Methods 6th edition -- Manuscript and proofs (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. I, Lea & Febiger...
    - Folder 1, 1952 (Box 13)
      Ms.
    - Folder 2, [1954] (Box 13)
      Galley proofs
    - Folder 3, 1954 (Box 13)
      Page proofs
  - Hydrogen Ions: Their Determination and Importance in Pure and Industrial Chemistry, by Hubert T. S. Britton -- Review, [1956] (Box 13)
  - ["Illustrations of a Chemical Continuum"] -- Lecture notes, 1963 (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. II, ACS Maryland Section, Maryland Chemist Award
  - JHU Remsen Memorial Lectures -- Notes, [1950] (Box 13)
    introducing lecturer, E. C. Kendall
  - "Life Without Oxygen" (Box 13)
    -see Ser. V, Cohen, Barnett, "Life Without Oxygen, a Report of an Address..."
  - "A Little of the Perspective of Acid-Base and Oxidation-Reduction Equilibria -- Lecture abstract, 1936 (Box 13)
    Nichols Medal address
    -see also Ser. I, ACS New York Section, William H. Nichols Medal...
  - ["Leonor Michaelis: 1875-1949"] -- Manuscript, [1950] (Box 13)
  - "Notes on a Half-Century of Research, Teaching, and Administration"--Ms., [1962?] (Box 13)
    -see also Ser. I, "Notes..."
  - "On Mechanism in Oxidation-Reduction - A Reply to Dixon" -- Manuscript, n.d. (Box 13)
  - "On Some Elementary Propositions Revealed by Use of Microscopic Equilibrium Constants" -- Manuscript, n.d. (Box 13)
  - "On the Retirement of Doctor Lewis Hill Weed..." -- Manuscript, [1946] (Box 13)
  - "An Outline of the History of Studies on Anaerobiosis" -- Lecture abstracts, 1928 (Box 13)
  - [Oxidation-Reduction] -- Manuscript, [ca. 1927] (Box 13)
  - Oxidation-Reduction Potentials in Bacteriology and Biochemistry, by L. F. Hewitt -- Review, [ca. 1950] (Box 13)
    Galley proof
  - [Oxidation-Reduction Potentials of Organic Systems] -- Revision notes, [1961-1963?]; 14 folders (Box 14)
    -see also Ser. III, Miscellaneous Calculations
    -see also Ser. III Miscellaneous Notes from the Literature
  - [Oxidation-Reduction Systems] -- Manuscript, [ca. 1925] (Box 14)
  - pH Measurements. Their Theory and Practice, by Victor Gold -- Review, [1950] (Box 14)
  - Poetry, n.d. (Box 14)
  - "A Primer on pH" -- Notes, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Proteins and the Theory of Colloidal Behavior, by Jacques Loeb -- Review, [1922] (Box 15)
  - "Reduction of Dyes by Biological Systems and Some Remarks on the Mechanism" -- Lecture notes, 1927 (Box 15)
  - "Reduction Potentials in Bacterial Cultures and Their Relation to Anaerobiosis" -- Abstract (Box 15)
  - "Report of the Representative of the American Society of Biological Chemists on the Annual Meeting of the Division of Biology and Agriculture, National Research Council, Held May 2, 1952" -- Manuscript (Box 15)
  - "Review of the Present Arrangements for Handling Information on Antimalarial Drugs" -- Manuscript (Box 15)
    Antimalarial drug prog.
  - "A Series of Studies of a Chemical Continuum" -- Abstract, n.d. (Box 15)
  - "Some Reflections on the Coupling of Chemical Processes and the Biochemical Implications" -- Lecture abstract and notes, 1952, 1954 (Box 15)
    2 versions of Remsen Memorial Lecture
  - "Studies on Oxidation-Reduction on Mechanism" (with Barnett Cohen and H. D. Gibbs) -- Manuscript (Box 15)
  - "A Survey of Antimalarial Drugs, 1941-1945: History of the Organizations" -- Manuscript, n.d.; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Topics in Physical Chemistry -- Manuscript, n.d. (Box 15)
    corrections
- Series V. Works by others, 1921-1952; 1 box, 0.25 lin. feet
  Handwritten manuscripts, typescripts, and one transcript, which chiefly comprise conference reports and papers describing research. A good portion of the material in this series resulted from the National Academy of Sciences / National Research Council antimalarial drug program. Papers covering other subjects were authored by Jonas S. Friedenwald, Karl Sollner, Joseph and Dorothy Moyle Needham, and R. E. Tarbett. The Friedenwald papers, three in number, concern the elementary theory of enzymatic activity and were co-authored with Gertrude Maengwyn-Davies. Also included is a 1952 manuscript by John Fuller Taylor entitled, "Wm. Mansfield Clark - An Appreciation." There is other biographical information about Clark to be found in notes by Donald D. Van Slyke and A. Baird Hastings. Two other items of note are humorous in nature. First, a handwritten manuscript by R. Keith Cannan entitled, "Studies on Ectoplasm...," and a printed sheet entitled, "The Turbo-Encabulator."
  - "Notes on Determination of Biochemical Oxygen Demand" -- Manuscript, [1925]; Burroughs, Lillian (Box 16)
  - Bush, Vannevar (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, NAS [Frank B.] Jewett and [Vannevar] Bush, "Proceedings of a Conference..."
  - "Studies on Ectoplasm..." -- Manuscript, n.d.; [Cannan, R. Keith] (Box 16)
    Humorous
  - "The Use of a Mediator in Determining the Oxidation-Reduction Potentials of Sulfhydryl Compounds", 1948; Caraway, Wendell T. (Box 16)
  - -see Ser. V, NRC Antimalarial Drug Program. "The Present Status...", Carden, George A. (Box 16)
  - "Applications of Hydrogen-Ion Concentration in Bacteriology" -- Manuscript, 1928; Cohen, Barnett (Box 16)
  - "Life Without Oxygen: Prof. Clark Addresses Washington Chemists" -- Report, 1924; Cohen, Barnett (Box 16)
  - "An Introductory Survey of the Influence of pH on the Lysis of Red Cells by Pneumococcal Hemolysin" -- Manuscript, [1947]; Cowgill, Robert W. (Box 16)
  - "Elementary Kinetic Theory of Enzymatic Activity: Influence of pH" -- Manuscript, n.d.; Friedenwald, Jonas S.; Maengwyn-Davies, Gertrude (Box 16)
  - "Elementary Kinetic Theory of Enzymatic Activity: First Order Theory" -- Manuscript, n.d.; Friedenwald, Jonas S.; Maengwyn-Davies, Gertrude (Box 16)
  - "Elementary Kinetic Theory of Enzymatic Activity: Second Order Theory" -- Manuscript, Friedenwald, Jonas S.; Maengwyn-Davies, Gertrude (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, NRC Antimalarial Drug Program. Reports by...
  - Hanes, Frederic M. (Box 16)
  - "The Scientific Career and Achievements of William Mansfield Clark, Nichols Medal Talk..." -- Speech, 1936; [Hastings, A. Baird] (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, NAS Selman A. Waksman and Elizabeth S. Horning. "Distribution..."
  - Horning, Elizabeth S. (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, NAS Frank B. Jewett, "Committee on Postwar Research..."
    -see Ser. V, NAS [Frank B.] Jewett and [Vannevar] Bush, "Proceedings of Conference..."
  - Jewett, Frank B. (Box 16)
    Includes WMC's comments, 11 pages.
  - "Interim Report of the Committee to Consider the Situation in Bacteriology", [1950]; JHU Medical School (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, Friedenwald, Jonas S. "Elementary Enzymatic..."
  - Maengwyn-Davies, Gertrude (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, Antimalarial Drug Program. Reports by...
    -see also Ser. II, Conference on Biological Antioxidants (Third)
  - Marshall, E. K., Jr. (Box 16)
  - "The Mechanism of Autoxidation and the Action of an Antioxidant" -- Lecture abstract, [1948]; Michaelis, Leonor (Box 16)
  - "Committee on Postwar Research..." -- Report, 1944; Jewett, Frank B. (Frank Baldwin), 1917-; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.) (Box 16)
  - "Proceedings of Conference to Consider Needs for Post-War Research and Development for the Army and the Navy" -- Transcript, 1944; Bush, Vannevar, 1890-1974; Jewett, Frank B. (Frank Baldwin), 1917-; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.) (Box 16)
    -see also Ser. I, NRC (14, 22 Dec. 1944)
  - "Distribution of Antagonistic Fungi in Nature and their Antibiotic Action" -- Manuscript, [1942]; Horning, Elizabeth S.; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); Waksman, Selman A., (Selman Abraham), 1888-1973 (Box 16)
  - [Manual for Laboratory Technicians (TM 8-227)], Chap. 3, Sec. V, "Acid-Base Indicators and Their Use in pH Measurements and Acid-Alkali Titrations" -- Manuscript, [1944]; National Research Council (U.S.) (Box 16)
    Parts 1 and 2
  - "Comments Upon Preliminary Evaluations of New Antimalarial Drugs" (Malaria Report No. 72, Survey Bulletin No. 11), January 20, 1944; National Research Council (U.S.). Antimalarial Drug Program. (Box 16)
  - "The Present Status of the Chemotherapy of Malaria" -- Manuscript, n.d.; National Research Council (U.S.). Antimalarial Drug Program. (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, Needham, Joseph and Dorothy Moyle Needham, "The Hydrogen Ion Concentration..."
  - Reports by William Mansfield Clark, Frederic W. Hanes, E. K. Marshall, Jr., and James A. Shannon, 14 October 1943; National Research Council (U.S.). Antimalarial Drug Program. (Box 16)
  - "Final Report, October 3, 1942", National Research Council (U.S.). Division of Chemistry and Chemical Technology. Committee on the Toxicity of Commerical Atabrine. (Box 16)
  - Needham, Dorothy Moyle (Box 16)
  - "The Hydrogen Ion Concentration and the Oxidation-Reduction Potential of the Cell Interior: a Micro-Injection Study" -- Manuscript, [1925]; Needham, Dorothy Moyle; Needham, Joseph, 1900- (Box 16)
  - "Studies on Oxidation-Reduction," IX-X, by [William] Mansfield Clark, et al. -- Review, 1926; Needham, Dorothy Moyle; Needham, Joseph, 1900- (Box 16)
  - "Publications and Events Relating to the Use of Plant Growth Regulating Compounds as a Means of Weed Control" -- Manuscript, 1944 (Box 16)
    -see also Ser. I, US Public Health Service
  - Shannon, James A. (Box 16)
    -see also Ser. I, Taylor, John Fuller
  - "Some Remarks Concerning the Measurement of Ion Activities in Colloidal Systems and the Suspension Effect" -- Manuscript, [1952]; Sollner, Karl (Box 16)
  - "Outline and Recommendations Covering Experimental Work in Connection with the Application of Certain Principles of Physical Chemistry to Water Treatment" -- Manuscript, 1921; Tarbett, R. E. (Box 16)
  - "Wm. Mansfield Clark - An Appreciation" -- Manuscript, [1952]; Taylor, John Fuller (Box 16)
    -see also Ser. I, Van Slyke, Donald D.
  - "The Turbo-Encabulator" -- Printed sheet, [ca. 1946?] (Box 16)
    -see Ser. V, NAS Selman A. Waksman and Elizabeth S. Horning, "Distribution of Antagonistic Fungi in Nature..."
  - "Experiment Biochemical Oxygen Demand" -- Manuscript, 1921; [US Public Health Service] (Box 16)
  - "Notes on the Personal Career of William Mansfield Clark, Nichols Medalist..." -- Speech notes, 1936; [Van Slyke, Donald D.] (Box 16)
  - Waksman, Selman A. (Box 16)
- Series VI. Photographs, 1929-1945; 1 box, 0.25 lin. feet
  Black and white photographic prints and negatives, and one 8mm color movie (1 reel; unidentified subject). The bulk of the prints show Clark's laboratory at the Johns Hopkins University Medical School, and include both staff members, and lab apparatus. There are also prints marked U.S.D.A. and labeled "Potassium Indigotine," a photo of a galvanometer, a photo of a portrait of Edwards A. Park, and miscellaneous images which include one of a large group of people (perhaps family members) gathered around a dinner table, and of the Czechoslovakia pavilion at a World's Fair. A large print (ca. 8" X 34"), now in several pieces, shows a group of people posed in front of a building, perhaps at the Johns Hopkins University Medical School or a U.S. Government facility. Clark and Barnett Cohen are close to the center of this print. The negatives, all of which are 4" X 5" show lecture or class notes on blackboards. The first group of 17 negatives was labeled "carbohydrates," and the second group of 9 negatives, "introduction and fats (I)." A photo (8" X 10") of a commemorative memento for the fiftieth anniversary of the American Physiological Society is also included.
  - American Physiological Society, 1938 (Box 17)
  - Bowditch, H. P. (Box 17)
    -see Ser. VI, American Physiological Society
  - Clark, William Mansfield, 1929, n.d. (Box 17)
    -see also Ser. VI, [JHU Medical School], Clark's Laboratory Staff
  - Cohen, Barnett, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Daveron, Solon Alexander, 1931 (Box 17)
  - Galvanometer, [1929] (Box 17)
  - Hellerman, Leslie (Box 17)
    -see Ser. VI, [JHU Medical School], Clark's Laboratory Staff
  - [JHU Medical School], Clark's Lab Staff], 1930, 1945, n.d. (Box 17)
  - [JHU Medical School], Clark's Lecture Notes, n.d. (Box 17)
    1 print and 26 negs.
  - [JHU Medical School], Laboratory Interiors, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Martin, H. N. (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 17)
  - Mitchell, S. Weir (Box 17)
  - Park, Edwards A., n.d. (Box 17)
  - Potassium Indigotine (Box 17)
  - Rich, Arnold R., 1952 (Box 17)
  - Unidentified Folder #1, n.d.; 8" X 34" print (in pieces) (Box 17)
  - Unidentified Folder #2, [ca. 1952?]; 8 mm. color movie, 1 reel (Kodachrome Safety film) (Box 17)